<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Andriy Koval</title>
    <link>/authors/admin/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Andriy Koval</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Andriy Koval</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/authors/admin/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Suppressing Small Counts for Public Release</title>
      <link>/publication/koval-2019-suppress-for-release/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/koval-2019-suppress-for-release/</guid>
      <description>Demonstrates the methods of suppressing small counts in a provincial surveillance system in preparation of data for public release.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Multi-Study Coordinated Meta-Analysis of Pulmonary Function and Cognition in Aging</title>
      <link>/publication/duggan-2018-pulmonary-cognition-aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/duggan-2018-pulmonary-cognition-aging/</guid>
      <description>In this second paper of a two-paper series, we conducted a coordinated analysis and summary meta-analysis of new results on the aging-related dynamics linking pulmonary function and cognitive performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Display Jupyter Notebooks with Academic</title>
      <link>/post/jupyter/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/jupyter/</guid>
      <description>Learn how to blog in Academic using Jupyter notebooks</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Academic: the website builder for Hugo</title>
      <link>/post/getting-started/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/getting-started/</guid>
      <description>Create a beautifully simple website in under 10 minutes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Independent and Interactive Impacts of Hypertension and Diabetes Mellitus on Verbal Memory</title>
      <link>/publication/kelly-2016-hypertension-diabetes-memory/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/kelly-2016-hypertension-diabetes-memory/</guid>
      <description>The study explored the effects of living with Hypertension and Diabetes Mellitus on declarative memory performace using data from longitudinal studies from England, Sweden, and the United States.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/authors/admin/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 May 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/authors/admin/</guid>
      <description>I am a data scientist with background in quantitative methods and interest in data-driven models of human aging.
I received my Ph.D. in Quantitative Methods in 2014 from Vanderbilt University, where I studied under Dr. Joe Rodgers, specializing in statistical modeling, design of graphical displays of information, and reproducible research. In August of the same year I joined the Integrative Analysis of Longitudinal Studies of Aging (IALSA) network (NIH/NIA P01AG043362) at the University of Victoria (UVic), directed by Dr.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>